A new and altogether different screen excitement!
Psycho is a horror, thriller, mystery film directed by Alfred Hitchcock.
When larcenous real estate clerk Marion Crane goes on the lam with a wad of cash and hopes of starting a new life,
she ends up at the notorious Bates Motel, where manager Norman Bates cares for his housebound mother.
Norman Bates, played by Anthony Perkins.
Marion Crane, played by Janet Leigh.
Lila Crane, played by Vera Miles.
Sam Loomis, played by John Gavin.
Milton Arbogast, played by Martin Balsam.
Al Chambers, played by John McIntire.
Psycho is a 1960 American horror film produced and directed by Alfred Hitchcock.
The screenplay, written by Joseph Stefano, was based on the
1959 novel of the same name by Robert Bloch.
The film stars Anthony Perkins, Janet Leigh, Vera
Miles, John Gavin and Martin Balsam.
The plot centers on an encounter between on-the-run embezzler Marion Crane (Leigh),
shy motel proprietor Norman Bates (Perkins) and his disturbed mother.
A private investigator (Balsam), Marion's lover Sam Loomis (Gavin) and
her sister Lila (Miles) investigate her disappearance.
Psycho was seen as a departure from Hitchcock's previous film, North by Northwest (1959), as it was filmed on a
small budget in black-and-white by the crew of his television series Alfred Hitchcock Presents.
Initially, the film divided critics due to its controversial subject matter, but audience
interest and outstanding box-office returns prompted a major critical re-evaluation.
Psycho was a massive commercial success; from a budget of $806,947 ($6.2 million with 2025 inflation), the film gained $50
million ($384.5 million with 2025 inflation) at the box office, worldwide, not including the money made with rentals.
Psycho was nominated for four Academy Awards, including Best Director
for Hitchcock and Best Supporting Actress for Leigh.
Psycho is now considered one of Hitchcock's best films, and is
arguably his most famous and influential work.
It has been hailed as a major work of cinematic art by international film critics and scholars who praise its
slick direction, tense atmosphere, impressive camerawork, memorable score and iconic performances.
Additionally, the shower scene has become one of
the best-known in all of cinema.
It is regarded as "the most heavily analyzed film in the long career of the most investigated director
in the history of American film" and often ranked among the greatest films of all time.
It set a new level of acceptability for violence, deviant behavior and sexuality in American films,
and has been considered to be one of the earliest examples of the slasher film genre.
After Hitchcock's death in 1980, Universal Pictures produced follow-ups: three
sequels, a remake, a made-for-television spin-off and a television series.
In 1992, the Library of Congress deemed the film "culturally, historically, or aesthetically
significant" and selected it for preservation in the United States National Film Registry.
The film explores themes of hotel, clerk, detective, shower, arizona.
The tone is dark and mind_bending and thought_provoking.